Cuba Subject Files, Inclusive: 1962-2004, Bulk: 1975-1998
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Cuba Subject Files
Inclusive: 1962-2004, Bulk: 1975-1998
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
5
Keston Institute, 1969 -
4 A4 document boxes
The Cuba Subject Files contain a variety of materials pertaining to political prisoners, international relations, and religion in the country.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the name changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist and totalitarian countries. The Keston Archive and Library houses numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
Keston collected documents dated from 1962 to 2004 reflecting the political and religious climate in Cuba.
After landing on the Cuban coast in 1492, Christopher Columbus claimed the island for Spain. Cuba remained under Spanish rule until 1898 following the Spanish-American War. The Treaty of Paris established Cuba’s independence, but for three-and-a-half years Cuba remained under United States military rule. Not until 1902 did Cuba become an independent republic.
Throughout the first half of the 20th century, Cuba saw the rise of several leaders. In 1953, revolutionaries, including Fidel Castro, led an attack on the Moncada Barracks near Santiago de Cuba. The Batista government quickly halted the attack resulting in the death of several insurgents and the imprisonment of Fidel Castro who was sentenced to 15 years. In 1955, Castro was released and exiled to Mexico where he and his brother Raúl met Argentine revolutionary Ernesto “Che” Guevara. In 1956, Fidel Castro led a group of 82 men to Cuba aboard the yacht Granma. Again Batista forces killed many of the fighters. However, Castro escaped with a dozen men and began a guerilla campaign. With the growing resistance, an unstable military force, and international pressure, Batista fled Cuba on January 1, 1959, and Castro took control.
Although initially supporting the revolution, United States ties became tense soon after Fidel Castro took power. Diplomatic relations between the two countries officially dissolved in 1961. The US imposed sanctions leading to a total ban on trade that continued into the 21st century.
In 1961, the failed Bay of Pigs Invasion further strained relations. The Invasion was an attempt by the US government to arm militant Cubans in an effort to overthrow the Communist regime. The Cuban Missile Crisis, also known as the October Crisis, occurred because Cuba agreed to allow the Soviet Union to deploy missiles on the island. The United States established a naval blockade that isolated Cuba from the Soviet shipments. The stalemate continued until delicate negotiations resulted in the Soviets agreeing to remove missiles already in Cuba while the United States pledged not to invade Cuba without provocation and to remove US missiles from Turkey.
Many Cuban citizens fled under Castro’s socialist regime. Over several decades, they found homes in countries such as Spain, Mexico, Italy, and Canada. Cuban Jews were allowed to emigrate to Israel, and the majority of the island’s 10,000 Jews eventually left. Between 1959 and 1993, nearly 1.2 million Cubans relocated to the United States. In 1965, Cuba and the United States agreed to permit Cubans to emigrate, and by 1971, more than 250,000 Cubans had traveled to the United States on so-called “Freedom Flights.”
During the 1970s and 1980s, the island nation became embroiled in international conflicts. Desiring to spread its revolutionary ideals, Cuba aided in conflicts throughout Africa and in South and Central America. Cuba provided military support, as well as assistance with health and education. In some cases, young people from these countries were educated in Cuba. Ultimately, Cuba supported 17 liberation movements, including those in Angola, Ethiopia, Nicaragua, and the Congo. The Angolan Civil War and the Ogaden War, also known as the Ethio-Somali War, saw tens of thousands of troops on the ground. Cuban support in other nations included aid, military training, and weapons.
In 2008, after ruling Cuba for nearly 60 years and in ill health, Fidel Castro stepped down as president. His younger brother Raúl succeeded him as president. Fidel Alejandro Castro Ruz died on November 25, 2016.
Scope and Content
Cuba subject files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, radio broadcast transcripts, background briefs, and periodicals.
The materials cover the period from 1962-2004 with the bulk from 1975-1998. The majority pertain to political prisoners, international relations, and religion. The materials related to political prisoners include, but are not limited to, prison conditions, treatment of prisoners, sentences and releases, and individual prisoners. Ricardo Bofill and Armando Valladares have the largest representation, but others include Jorge Valls Arango, Ariel Hidalgo Guillen, Angel Cuadra Landrove, Huber Matos, Eloy Gutierrez Menoyo, and others. International relations materials focus mostly on relationships with the Soviet Union and the United States, but Cuba’s dealings with African and South American countries are also represented. Religious items include information on several denominations, but prominently the Catholic Church and Pope John Paul II’s papal visit in 1998.
Arrangement
The Keston center received the Cuba materials organized into the categories Cuba General Files and Cuba Religious Files. Within these categories, all materials were organized chronologically. This organization has mostly been preserved but has been divided further into specific thematic subjects and denominations.
The Cuba Subject Files are currently arranged into two series: I. General and II. Denominational materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 5.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016.; John Paul II, Pope, 1920-2005 -- Travel -- Cuba.
Places
Cuba -- Foreign relations -- 1959-1990.; Cuba -- Foreign relations -- 1990-; Cuba -- History -- 1959-1990.; Cuba -- History -- 1990-; Cuba -- Politics and government -- 1959-1990.; Cuba -- Politics and government -- 1990-
Subjects
Christianity -- Cuba.; Church and state -- Cuba.; Papal visits -- Cuba.; Persecution -- Cuba.; Political prisoners -- Cuba.; Socialism and religion -- Cuba.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Periodicals.; Radio scripts.
- General, 1962-2004; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  General Cuba subject files contain information on history, Fidel Castro, government, church-state relations, oppressive practices and political prisoners, international relations, emigration, communism, human rights, religion, children and culture.
  - General, 1962-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Individuals: Castro, Fidel, 1965-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Government, 1968-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Elections, 1992-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Espionage, 1973-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Emigration, 1966-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Constitution, 1970-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Church and State, 1973-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Basic Rights and Freedoms, 1977-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Law and Religion, 1975-1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices, 1983-2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Political Prisoners, 1963-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Political Prisoners, 1987-1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Political Prisoners: Arango, Jorge Valls, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Political Prisoners: Bofill, Ricardo, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Political Prisoners: Guillen, Ariel Hidalgo, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Political Prisoners: Landrove, Angel Cuadra, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Political Prisoners: Matos, Huber, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Political Prisoners: Menoyo, Eloy Gutierrez, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Political Prisoners: Valladares, Armando, 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - International Relations, 1965-1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - International Relations: Africa, 1976-1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - International Relations: Angola, 1976-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - International Relations: Canada, 1973-1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - International Relations: China, 1966-1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - International Relations: Ethiopia, 1977-1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - International Relations: Grenada, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - International Relations: Nicaragua, 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - International Relations: Spain, 1977-1990 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - International Relations: Somalia, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - International Relations: South America, 1982-1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - International Relations: Soviet Union, 1970-1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Castro and Perestroika, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - International Relations: United States of America, 1962-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - International Relations: Vatican, 1965-1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Non-aligned Countries, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Drug Smuggling and Expulsions form the State, 1983-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Western Reactions, Interventions, Pronouncements, and Criticism, 1970-1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - UN and UN Specialized Agencies, 1983-1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Commission on Human Rights Report (1 of 2), 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Commission on Human Rights Report (2 of 2), 1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Activities Disapproved by the State, Dissidents, and Protests, 1980-1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Human Rights Committee, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Defections, 1964-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Religion: General, 1966-1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ecumenical Movement, 1973-1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bible, 1954-1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Biblical Societies, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Visits, 1971-2004 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Oppressive Practices Relating to Religious Activity, 1966-1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Cuba's Easement of Restrictions on the Church, 1979-1998 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Religious Revival, 1983-2001 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Theological Education, 1975-1997 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Witchcraft and Voodoo, 1968-1999 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Religion and youth and children, 1976-1998 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Abolishment and Return of Christmas to Cuba, 1970-2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ideology, Communism, and Ethics, 1963-1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Party Congress and Decisions, 1975-1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Communism and Christianity, 1972-1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ideological and Religious Broadcasts from the West, 1980-1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Agriculture, 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Economy, 1976-1997 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Health, Sport, and Leisure, 1977-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Tourism, 1978-2001 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - National Information Service: General, 1991-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Culture, 1971-1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Literature, 1963-1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Individual Publications: Fidel and Religion, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Arts, Architecture, and Music, 1970-1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Women, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Youth, Children, 1966-1998 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Party and Other Youth Organizations, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Everday Life, 1969-1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Denominational, 1954-2003; 2
  Cuba’s denominational subject files include categories pertaining to particular denominational activities within the country.
  - Adventists, 1984-2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Anglicans, 1980-1999 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Baptists, 1965-2000 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Evangelicals, 1971-1999 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Jehovah's Witness, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Jews, 1973-2000 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Lutherans, 1973-1990 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Methodists, 1966-1999 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Pentecostals, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Presbyterians, 1972-1998 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Roman Catholic: General, 1966-1998 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Individuals: Cardinal Ortega, Jaime, 1981-1999 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Individuals: Mother Theresa, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Individuals: Paya, Oswaldo, 1992-2003 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Individuals: Pope John Paul II and his Papal visit to Cuba, 1984-1999 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Individuals: Pope John Paul II and his Papal visit to Cuba, Spanish Newspapers, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Catholic Patriarchate, 1970-1998 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Church-State Relations, 1974-2001 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oppresive Practices Relating to Religious Activity, 1974-2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Individual Catholic Clergy: Masvidal, Eduardo, 1974-1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Poor Quality Originals, 1954-1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)